<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss
  version="2.0"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>weathering</title>
    <description>At the intersection of weather forecasting, technology, and the unknowable. A scattered mix of academic papers, good books, philosophy, and the human relationship with weather. Hosted by Marshall, Marta, and Alden.</description>
    <link>https://dynamical.org//podcast</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 19:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <itunes:author>Marshall, Marta, and Alden</itunes:author>
    <itunes:summary>At the intersection of weather forecasting, technology, and the unknowable. A scattered mix of academic papers, good books, philosophy, and the human relationship with weather.</itunes:summary>
    <itunes:category text="Science">
      <itunes:category text="Earth Sciences"/>
    </itunes:category>
    <itunes:category text="Technology"/>
    <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
    <itunes:image href="https://dynamical.org//assets/weathering/weathering_logo.png"/>
      
      <item>
        <title>End-to-end data-driven weather prediction</title>
        <description>
          
            Where does the end begin? Where does the end end? And what the HELL is happening in the middle? These are some of the questions we tackle in this episode as we explore Aardvark Weather, an end-to-end...
          
        </description>
        <content:encoded>
          <![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Where does the end begin? Where does the end end? And what the HELL is happening in the middle?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of the questions we tackle in this episode as we explore Aardvark Weather, an end-to-end forecasting system. End-to-end models are super cool, and likely to be the future of weather forecasting—but they also revitalize old questions about transparency, end-user trust, and the fidelity &amp;amp; availability of raw observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join us as we unpack what an end-to-end model is, the Aardvark Weather approach, and how these models at-large might shape the landscape of forecasting (And books. Always books.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Featured paper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-025-08897-0#Sec2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End-to-end data-driven weather prediction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Forest Unseen&lt;/em&gt; by David George Haskell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;https://harpers.org/archive/2024/07/the-gods-of-logic-benjamin-labatut-ai/&quot;&gt;The Gods of Logic&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; by Benjamín Labatut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moon of the Crusted Snow&lt;/em&gt; by Waubgeshig Rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.incompleteideas.net/IncIdeas/BitterLesson.html&quot;&gt;The Bitter Lesson&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; by Rich Sutton&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
]]>
        </content:encoded>
        <link>https://dynamical.org/podcast/002/</link>
        <guid>https://dynamical.org/podcast/002/</guid>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
          <enclosure url="https://dynamical.org/assets/weathering/002.mp3" type="audio/mpeg" length="0"/>
        
        
        <itunes:author>Marshall, Marta, and Alden</itunes:author>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        
          <itunes:episode>002</itunes:episode>
        
      </item>
      
      <item>
        <title>The limits of predictability</title>
        <description>
          
            How far into the future can we actually predict the weather? Typically, this question is rhetorical, a slight (or smite⚡) against meteorologists everywhere after someone’s wedding gets rained out. But...
          
        </description>
        <content:encoded>
          <![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;How far into the future can we actually predict the weather? Typically, this question is rhetorical, a slight (or smite⚡) against meteorologists everywhere after someone’s wedding gets rained out. But in this inaugural episode of &lt;em&gt;Weathering&lt;/em&gt;, we’re asking in earnest—what is the horizon for accurate weather forecasts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we look at a paper from the University of Washington (link below) that suggests the limit might be more than double the long-held belief of fourteen days. Thus, too, challenging the foundational theory of chaos—“the butterfly effect”—that has informed how we think and forecast weather since it was coined in the 1970s. We examine the methods that the researchers use and engage in some armchair philosophy: What does chaos mean if our foundational example of chaos—weather—is actually predictable? Is there a difference between chaos and predictability? And how might knowing next month’s weather change our relationship to the environment and weather itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t promise you answers, we didn’t even articulate the questions that well, but we can promise to add to your never-ending TBR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Featured paper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Testing the Limit of Atmospheric Predictability With a Machine Learning Weather Model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2504.20238&quot;&gt;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2504.20238&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science and Method&lt;/strong&gt; by Henri Poincaré&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Chaos theory before it was chaos theory.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Isaac&#39;s Storm&lt;/strong&gt; by Erik Larson&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The 1900 Galveston hurricane through the eyes of meteorologist Isaac Cline, revealing the human and scientific failures that led to the deadliest natural disaster in U.S. history.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immeasurable Weather: Settler Colonialism and the American Weather Enterprise&lt;/strong&gt; by Sara J. Grossman&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Weather science in the U.S. is entangled with settler colonialism (omg no way).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strange as This Weather Has Been&lt;/strong&gt; by Ann Pancake&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A novel set during the coal boom in southern Appalachia, centered on mountaintop removal mining and catastrophic flooding. You will weep.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“A Sound of Thunder”&lt;/strong&gt; by Ray Bradbury&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A short story in which stepping on a butterfly in the past alters the future. Published BEFORE the term was coined, and that’s Bradbury for ya.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
]]>
        </content:encoded>
        <link>https://dynamical.org/podcast/001/</link>
        <guid>https://dynamical.org/podcast/001/</guid>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
          <enclosure url="https://dynamical.org/assets/weathering/001.mp3" type="audio/mpeg" length="0"/>
        
        
        <itunes:author>Marshall, Marta, and Alden</itunes:author>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        
          <itunes:episode>001</itunes:episode>
        
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>